Guide to the Paccarik Orue Photographs, 2012-2014 RL.11280
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paccarik Orue Photographs
2012-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Orue, Paccarik
RL.11280
1.0 Linear Feet
San Francisco-based photographer Paccarik Orue was born and raised in Lima, Peru. His series "El Muqui" won the 2016 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of Color. "El Muqui" comprises 40 color photographs taken between 2012 and 2014 in the Peruvian mining city Cerro de Pasco. The photographs document life in the city, which "due to economic interests and expansion of the mine, [is] doomed to disappear." He writes "it was essential to find myself and reconnect with my Peruvian roots and heritage...and gives me the opportunity to continue making work of social relevance."
Arrangement
Arranged by creator.
Biographical / Historical
Paccarik Orue was born and raised in Lima, Peru and resides in San Francisco, California. He has a BFA from the Academy of Art University. His work has been shown at Blue Sky Gallery, SF Camerawork, Contemporary Art Center New Orleans, Rayko Photo Center, SOMArts, Book & Job Gallery and it has been featured in The New York Times, PDN, Juxtapox, KQED, Conscientious, Lenscratch, Feature Shoot among others. He was selected by PDN as one of the 30 Emerging Photographers to Watch in 2016 and has been awarded En Foco’s New Works Photography Fellowship Award (2013-2014.) His first monograph, There Is Nothing Beautiful Around Here was published by Owl & Tiger Books in 2012.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Paccarik Orue Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016.
Collection Overview
The Paccarik Orue Photographs contain his photography portfolio "El Muqui," which won the 2016 Archive of Documentary Arts Collection Award for Documentarians of Color. The project contains (40) 14x14” color prints printed using an Epson 7890 printer and Epson Ultrachrome K3 ink on Ilford Galerie Prestige Gold Fibre Silk from 6x6 scans of 120 Kodak Portra 400 film.
Orue provided the following abstract of his work:
El Muqui
Cerro de Pasco is an historical city of 80,000 people in the Peruvian Andes, situated on top of one of the biggest sources of income for the Peruvian government: mineral deposits. Due to economic interests and the expansion of the mine, the city is doomed to disappear. My series El Muqui, narrates a story of daily lives and environmental concerns, combined with elements such as the local folklore and cultural traditions.
“El Muqui” is a folkloric character in the Andean mines who is highly respected, even feared, by miners, and has a strong moral code. Popular tales talk about how he is aware of the miners’ desires and actions, but also playful with children. El Muqui is the center of many of the celebrations and traditions in Cerro de Pasco.
This is an important project for me because after living in the US for half of my life, I felt that it was essential to find myself and reconnect with my Peruvian roots and heritage. El Muqui also gives me the opportunity to continue making work of social relevance, and to give people, like the inhabitants of Cerro de Pasco, a voice that they do not have. As the mining activity increases, the Peruvian government is planning to relocate the city, so this project documents a city that will cease to exist as it is today.
Documentary Photography; Cerro de Pasco (Peru); Peru -- pictorial works; Andes Region -- social life and customs; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Orue, Paccarik
- El Muqui, 2012-2014; 40 Photographic Prints
  - Amanecer Cerreño, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hombre con tuba y chuyo, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Viviendas y desmonte, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tajo Raul Rojas, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Propiedad Privada #1, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cruz de Paragsha, niños, cometas y desmonte, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Niño lobo, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Secando uniformes, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Fiesta de Las Cruces de Mayo, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ex-Laguna Quilacocha #2, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bailarina de Los Capullos, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baldes de agua, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Educación física, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Secando ropa y Charqui, 2103 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trombonista de la Polifónica Magistral, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Repartiendo queso y leche, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Después de la fiesta, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carnicero, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kiosko, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Niños con bicicletas, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dragón Cerreño, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campamento Mireno 1 de Mayo, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vizcacha Andina, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pieles, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Botas, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hombre con Chuyo, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Laguna Lulicocha, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mayordomos, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cruz de San Juan y Tajo Raul Rojas, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jugando voleibol, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ex Laguna Quilacocha, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Niña, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kaypin-Cruz, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Niños jugando en Champamarca, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reclutador, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - La Ultima Cena Cerreña, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tu y yo, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tumba, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Violinista (la ultima canción), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Laguna Patarocha, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)